now what if we have an absolute value
expression
with an inequality
what do we need to do
well we still need to write two
equations
the first one is going to remain the
same
now for the second one we need to do two
things
we need to change the positive five to a
negative five and
we need to change the direction of the
inequality
so that's important make sure you
understand that
and then after that just it
five plus one is six and then let's
divide by three
so x is greater than two
now for the other one negative five plus
one
is negative four and if we divided by
three we're going to get a fraction x is
less than negative four thirds
now because we're dealing with
inequalities we need to plot the
solution on a number line
so we need two negative four thirds is
about negative one point three which is
between negative one and two
so x
is greater than two
which means that we have an open circle
at two shaded towards the right and x is
less than negative four thirds which is
about negative one point three
so it's an open circle
shaded towards the left
now the solution
using interval
let's write it up here it's going to be
negative infinity
to negative 4 over 3
and then union
2 to infinity
so here's the 2 to infinity part
and here's the negative infinity to
negative four thirds
the open circle is at negative four
thirds just keep that in mind
let's try another example
feel free to pause the video and work on
it
now right now we can't
write two equations yet
we need to get the absolute value
expression on one side of the equation
first
so first let's subtract both sides by
3.
so what we're going to have is negative
2 times the absolute value of 2x minus 1
is less than or equal to negative 10.
next
let's divide both sides
by negative two
so this will change the direction of the
inequality just keep that in mind
so the absolute value of two x minus one
is equal to or greater than
positive five
now since we have the absolute value
expression on one side by itself
with no other numbers outside of it
this is when we can write two equations
2x minus 1 is greater than or equal to 5
and 2x minus one is less than or equal
to negative five
don't forget to change the direction of
the inequality
so now let's add one
so two x is greater than or equal to six
and next let's divide by two so x is
equal to or greater than 3.
here we're going to add 1
so 2x is less than or equal to negative
4 and then divide by 2.
so x is less than or equal to negative
2.
so we have x is less than or equal to
negative two and x is equal to a greater
than three
so here's zero
here's negative two
and here's three
so x is equal to or greater than three
so we have a closed circle by three
shaded towards the right
x is equal to or less than negative two
so we have a closed circle shaded
towards left
so therefore the solution
is negative infinity to negative 2 with
a bracket
union
3 to infinity